[SPEAKER_01]: So, let's say that someone has been reading the suttas and they have a small or a large amount of clarity regarding what the Buddhist teaching is.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're able to explain it to others.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're able to explain it to themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything makes sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yet, if they ask themselves honestly,
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether they're free from suffering or whether they're still subject to suffering, it becomes clear that they aren't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is it then that needs to improve or evolve further for that information that a person has to become an insight, a direct insight that actually liberates them?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, how to move from ideas, from the right ideas, to insight.
[SPEAKER_00]: I guess a lowball kind of approach to that would be to say, well, the ideas you have, are you applying them to the extent that you understand them?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what would be one common idea that, you know, every Buddhist knows, but might not apply?
[SPEAKER_00]: For example, like, you know what... you might not know what greed means in, like, the truest, most kind of enlightened sense, but you have some idea of what greed is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That aligns with your own experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, are you giving into that, when it arises?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or are you not giving into it?
[SPEAKER_00]: I guess, that could be one avenue of questioning.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, because the thing is, the people would
[SPEAKER_01]: Become content with where the point where they have reached, because they would have realized that a change has factually occurred, compared to... very often, change has occurred in terms of... well, their opinions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, they... their opinions about things were...
[SPEAKER_01]: Reflecting back to where they were, it would become clear that they were very wrong in the past, compared to what it would be now, just on account of the information.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the crucial distinction there is that having an opinion in line with the teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: For example, in the suttas, you would see
[SPEAKER_01]: Opinions that are very clearly not in line with the siddhas, like the ascetics of other sects, when they would go around saying that there is no kamma, there is no action, there is no fruits and results of good and bad actions, there is no mother, there is no father.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, in a modern sense, you might have people adhering to, I don't know, nihilism or
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, various sort of worldly ideologies, and you feel factually that you've been able to effect a change from that to, let's say, now your belief is anatta.
[SPEAKER_01]: You believe in anatta.
[SPEAKER_01]: You believe in the four noble truths.
[SPEAKER_01]: You believe in kamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: You believe in freedom from suffering and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the thing is, those are opinions, or those are beliefs.
[SPEAKER_01]: And view is something different.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, not necessarily different, but something deeper than that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can...
[SPEAKER_01]: The point being, changing your opinion is necessary for you to begin the practice in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: But your view has not necessarily changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the measurement of your view changing is... What is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, but that, like, what is the criteria for that, which we just mentioned?
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, well, you need to hear the true teaching and... No, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: The criteria for defining what is sotāpatti, like... because, again, you have the same opinion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you still... you also believe that there is suffering, there is... that craving is the origin of suffering, that the cessation of suffering is the escape.
[SPEAKER_02]: And now you're asking what's the difference between believing that...
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: ...and actually a noble disciple realizing the vulnerable truth.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you see, belief is something
[SPEAKER_02]: Colloquially speaking, you're not quite sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, something could be the case...
[SPEAKER_02]: But you're not 100% sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: You might have good reasons to believe a certain thing, and most of the time you can conduct yourself based on that belief, but that belief will always be bound up with a sense of doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: Belief and doubt go together.
[SPEAKER_02]: But now, when the Buddha talks about right view, that doesn't go together with that doubt which is on the side of belief.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, right view has that confidence or that certainty.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that is a distinction that we can make, it seems to me, between what is actually a right view, the saṃmadhīti of the sūtas, and the belief, the way people colloquially use it, like belief.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, okay, that's one angle from which you could approach it, which we can come back to later, but...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how does it feel?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the most...
[SPEAKER_01]: Because a person might... again, you might have studied Buddhism for so long and for 20-30 years, that you kind of feel like you don't have doubts about this anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, some of it might even have been confirmed by random, you know, little insights that you had here and there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I see.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can kind of convince yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, we've met people that they don't admit the fact that they're still subject to doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, then we have to come back to our discussion on authenticity.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, people need to be honest with themselves.
[SPEAKER_02]: Am I still liable to suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the criteria for who is a sotāpanna or not, more than just asking how sure am I of this, because, you know, many kind of... You can deceive yourself, like, okay, I'm really sure, but you might have not considered something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, later on, you might still be shaken.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, many people can be...
[SPEAKER_01]: You can express, like, you know, insane amounts of certainty in regards to various things, but the right view is measured by...
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, yes, you need some degree of authenticity, but more practically, are you still liable to suffer?
[SPEAKER_01]: In any shape or form.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if you ask yourself, do you still depend on certain coping mechanisms or certain strategies for you to escape that suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: And at the same time, you think that you're free from doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you have truly understood that craving is the root of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that doesn't do it together.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't have any need to run away from suffering, in that sense, if you have understood the escape.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's one of the clear signs that what you have more is a belief or is an opinion.
[SPEAKER_01]: And your view is still not in line with the Buddha's teaching fundamentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, back to what you said about doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is it that would then turn a belief, the same opinion or the same belief that you started from, so it's not that it changes, like you hear the teaching of the Buddha and it's in the content, like the phrasing and the
[SPEAKER_01]: The expression is the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like there was some hidden stanza or something that you would now come up with that you couldn't before.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's more, well, what is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: What's the difference?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is it that makes that belief turn into something that it's impossible to doubt?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it's got to be all-encompassing view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if it isn't, there's room for doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, of course, but how do you make it all-encompassing?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that has got to do with the yoniso manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, we can...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's exactly why the, so to say, there's two conditions for the arising of the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: One of them is the utterance of another through which you change your opinion, you could say, from the very start.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you don't have yonisonmanasikāra, then all you're left with is the utterance of another that now became your utterance.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it doesn't necessarily mean that it became integrated, let's say.
[SPEAKER_02]: It stays on the level of ideas.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you might genuinely hear something new, or somebody might confirm something that you already believed, and now you are more certain.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you agree with it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you agree with it, and so you now have more certainty, like, oh, this other person that I have great faith in says the same thing, but that's still not it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, or, even again, you had a completely wrong opinion, you changed it, but...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if that liability to doubt and suffering is still there, it hasn't permeated, like you said, it hasn't become all-encompassing, so that it becomes a view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, so, let's say...
[SPEAKER_01]: Common example, craving is suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a belief.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or the root of suffering is craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a belief or an opinion that almost every Buddhist might have.
[SPEAKER_01]: But why is it not all-encompassing, without just going to the textbook answer of Yoniso Manasikāra?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, there has to be a suitable basis, let's say, in one's experience, for those statements to land, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if someone is living a life that is rooted, by and large, in acting out of craving,
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, you can meet someone who is factually free from craving, and who tells you that craving is suffering, and then you might still agree with that on the level of ideas, failing to see that that's completely disconnected from how you conduct yourself in your daily life.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that discrepancy
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, so that would be, obviously, again, the first step.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you hear
[SPEAKER_01]: It becomes even more of an empty opinion if you're... if you quote-unquote believe in it, but your day-to-day actions are totally based on other assumptions that are contrary to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, let's say then that you have restrained your living
[SPEAKER_01]: To the best of your ability, to the point where you're aware, you live according to the idea or belief that you acquired, that craving is the root of suffering, and you never do anything that you know is rooted in craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, so what is left there?
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, this is...
[SPEAKER_00]: I was gonna say, like, this discrepancy that you mentioned.
[SPEAKER_00]: You still... you can kind of take that principle, I guess, and keep going with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Insofar as if you have the opinions, but your views... like, you can tell, okay, I'm not free from suffering, so my views aren't quite aligned with my opinions.
[SPEAKER_00]: That means I believe something that I don't actually
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, I say that I believe something, but I don't actually.
[SPEAKER_00]: I guess you could put it that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, trying to kind of recognize, okay, there is a discrepancy somewhere.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, what
[SPEAKER_00]: I guess one example that's probably super super common for most kind of most Buddhists is getting so used to just like denying, like, oh, no, there's no self, no self, no self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Being able to actually kind of say like, okay, well, let's stop dismissing that and actually look for, like,
[SPEAKER_00]: Clearly, I have self-view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, kind of letting that manifest in your experience, not just pushing it away because it's wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not in line with your belief.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if it was your view, you wouldn't have to do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's one important point.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to be willing to
[SPEAKER_01]: Accept, and that feeds back into that authenticity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Willing to accept that you still have the fundamental illness.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might have...
[SPEAKER_01]: The belief is on the level of, oh, look, that's the best doctor over there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's your belief.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's accurate.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you don't go through with the treatment, which will be painful, because, you know, it requires you to accept that you are sick.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's no longer just an impersonal acknowledgement of how great the doctor is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's now about you and your condition.
[SPEAKER_01]: It requires you then to have that authenticity to say, yes, it doesn't matter how much I agree with all the theory that this doctor talks about of how to cure this disease.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fundamentally, I am still not cured.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, ironically, you have to start by taking it quite personally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you use the beliefs to kind of cover up your wrong view,
[SPEAKER_01]: That's one of the main obstacles, because then you will...
[SPEAKER_01]: The belief is supposed to, like that external utterance of another, is supposed to be, for the lack of a better word, applied to the wrong understanding that you have, which means you need to have admitted to yourself that that wrong understanding is there, and that our wrong understanding will be sort of indirectly
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you don't allow suffering to arise to begin with, like, as you said, your first response is to get rid of it,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you have nothing further belief to, ironically, apply to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, there's no work for you to do, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is... but in a wrong way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, instead of no work to do because you got to the end, it's like no work to do because you're refusing to start.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just kind of a...
[SPEAKER_01]: Content, which is pointing to where the goal is, but not walking there yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the admission that has to come first.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have the opinion or the belief that the five aggregates are impermanent, that they're suffering, that they're not self.
[SPEAKER_01]: But my view is different.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if it wouldn't be, you would at least be a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you wouldn't have all the suffering that you have, clearly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, the right place for that belief, you'll start to see that that information that you have is not just something for you to, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, there's a trophy or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the stuff that you have to use, like a shovel, that you need to use in order to be digging.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, digging with a knife.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's through that belief or that opinion, it's telling you kind of where you're going to go.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you're just, again, satisfied with the content of the belief or the view, you're not going to be using it for the purpose that it actually is meant to fulfill.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the other thing as well is the liability to doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you will never transcend doubt by improving the opinion or improving the information to some theoretically perfect point.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's precisely by recognizing... Well, you would only be able to do that again if you have admitted to yourself that you're still liable to suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you realize what is doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is actually doubt?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it doubt that my opinion or information is not perfectly extensive and comprehensive?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or is it doubt that when my information or beliefs are not comprehensive enough, I resist that discomfort?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, on that level, you'll be able to now apply the information that craving is suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you would overcome doubt through that avenue, not by getting, you know, perfect definitions of the of the, I don't know, 115 types of suffering that correspond to the craving in such and such sense space or something, like some sort of Abhidhamma analysis.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be a concrete
[SPEAKER_01]: application of that belief in... okay, there is doubt, there is unpleasantness and discomfort on account of that doubt, and I know that anything that I do rooted in craving against the discomfort of that doubt, will be ironically against... well, will be perpetuating the wrong view, that it's the discomfort that is the suffering, not the resistance to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, see, you have the same belief,
[SPEAKER_01]: On paper, craving is suffering, and you will be applying it in a way that's actually growing the wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you still imply that it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: On some level, you imply, I am suffering because I'm not clear enough about how craving is suffering, on the level of information.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you don't see that it's actually... well, that's where yonisamādhi-sikāra would come in.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't see that it's actually you, here and now, in regards to that lack of knowledge, resisting that discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is your failure.
[SPEAKER_01]: The other thing I want to say is,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that craving that you have in relation to not knowing the answer to something, it needs to be kind of... the information is not applied to sort of get rid of it, which again would be falling into that
[SPEAKER_01]: Misapplication of the information to basically, like, deny the fact that you're sick as quickly as possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's, as we keep saying, it's for you to
[SPEAKER_01]: Practically speaking, be able to endure that discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you still have the background assumption that the information is sort of meant for the purpose of dealing with discomfort in that direct sense, like knocking it off, then that's going to be, again, still proliferating the same wrong view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, so the doctor can prescribe medicine and say these pills two times a day, those pills five times a day.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can have all that information.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you don't take them, it's not going to make any difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, or you take them when you want to take them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't take them in the...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the... the development of yoniso manasikāra, how does it start?
[SPEAKER_01]: Aha.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that, you know, mixed with that information you have, it can become the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or let's put it this way.
[SPEAKER_01]: What do the suttas define is the progression towards the purification view?
[SPEAKER_01]: What do the suttas define?
[SPEAKER_01]: As the progression towards... or the prerequisites for the purification of you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ah, what do the suttas say needs to happen first, before one's views can be purified?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Gradual training.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, but which means what in this case?
[SPEAKER_00]: Virtue, first and foremost.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to...
[SPEAKER_00]: If you just think of yoniso, manasikāra as kind of...
[SPEAKER_00]: perspective, then you need to kind of get your nose out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is going to mean restraining precepts first, refinement from there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so purification of views...
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so purification of views is not the first step in the Relay Chariot Sutta that the Sariputta was defining the steps of the training.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ironically, many people would think that you start from there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's where you would be endlessly just...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's almost like going back and forth in terms of beliefs and opinions, like, you know, reintegrating, syncretizing and mixing and matching.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, and that is precisely why it stays on the level of opinions and beliefs, and why it doesn't go further.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you... you will still have... so, that's the... another thing I want to mention.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will... inevitably, you will have views and opinions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why it's important to get the information from the outside.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you can't become a Buddha by yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to get that utterance of another.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't be able to arrive at it by yourself, but...
[SPEAKER_01]: That's another thing, like, important to recognize as well, because...
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, without that, how would you even know, for example, that virtue is important?
[SPEAKER_01]: How would you even know that what purification of mind entails, which is the second step?
[SPEAKER_01]: How would you even know that you're supposed to emphasize purification of virtue, which for most people would not be the first thing that comes to mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need the utterance of another for you to even start with these... with the graduate training, with all these prerequisites.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just that you...
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't emphasize it past the level where it motivates you to do these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, beyond that point, you realize, okay, I...
[SPEAKER_01]: I got enough information to recognize the importance of these things, and now, the purification of you will come, if I purify my virtue sufficiently, and as a result of purifying my virtue, not as a result of meditation techniques, I purify my mind as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you'll be able to
[SPEAKER_01]: See, that information that you obtained initially, you'll be able to see, as we say, on the right level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, it's, well, obviously, as this is to say, it's the five hindrances that prevent the seeing things as they are, quote-unquote.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not, again, through concentration practices, it's
[SPEAKER_01]: You could basically boil it down to saying it's your way of behaving in the world, including by mind, that goes against those principles that you
[SPEAKER_01]: Understand in theory, that's what the five hindrances are, in a very broad sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you... to the point where you can even be having the right information, that restlessness is unwholesome, craving is unwholesome, all these things are unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, with that information, you're acting out of the five hindrances.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how subtle it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: But, obviously, you won't be able to see that until you purify your virtue first.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why purification of mind comes second.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the graduate training always presents it in that order.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, but then, once those bases are covered, now you have a chance of factually even seeing what craving means.
[SPEAKER_01]: Before that, you couldn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, again, you have to ask yourself, like, so, because sometimes people have a
[SPEAKER_01]: Think that, okay, on account of this or other practice, they were able to see what craving is, but...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, did it actually require you to purify your virtue?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, do you see directly that without virtue, it would have been impossible for me to get to that point?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or does it feel like if I had just, you know, known one detail or another about this... the performance of this technique, I would have gone there without any virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: If that's the case, it means it's not the purification of you, at least, that's described in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, as he's saying, it's like... it's like you got to the to the second chariot without the first one.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's literally impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the simile it gives.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you take the first chariot, it takes you somewhere,
[SPEAKER_01]: But not past that point.
[SPEAKER_01]: From then on, you need to take the second chariot, which will take you to where the third chariot is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you magically were able to jump from the first to the third, that tells you that, well, that that's that's not the same training that we're that we're talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this kind of, this vaguely reminds me of just something I've been sort of thinking about the past few days.
[SPEAKER_00]: Kind of using weight loss as an analogy.
[SPEAKER_00]: How to put this...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, take somebody who wants to lose weight.
[SPEAKER_00]: You give them the option.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, you can just press this button and automatically you'll lose weight.
[SPEAKER_00]: They'll press it and, you know, a few months down the line they'll be in the same position they were before.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you want to lose weight,
[SPEAKER_00]: You kind of actually need to shift your goal, not to losing weight, but to having a lifestyle that is conducive to having a healthier body, to having a healthy active lifestyle, essentially.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if somebody can bring themselves to value that type of lifestyle,
[SPEAKER_00]: More or less, the issue is solved, even if they're still not at the kind of point of weight loss that they wanted to get to yet.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's about that mode of being.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what'll actually get you there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not just kind of the magical, like, snap of a finger, oh my gosh, I'm skinny.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, even if... You go celebrate with cake.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if technically, obviously, there isn't something that can take you to the right view by moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, even when people think they get these insights, if you get to the nitty-gritty details of it,
[SPEAKER_01]: They're contradictory with the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not in line with what the Buddha actually describes as the three characteristics, what he describes as the five aggregates, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even if, theoretically, it were possible to have a momentary insight of that kind, that is factually accurate, and then you were to lose it, well, the fact that
[SPEAKER_01]: The person wouldn't be putting the emphasis on the things that the Buddha did put the emphasis on, which is virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, like in this case, the healthy lifestyle, as you mentioned, means it's not actually the right thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, like, the Buddha would describe it's like... a sotāpanna is not just someone who has wholesome qualities.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's somebody who understands.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wholesome is wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unwholesome is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: The root of the wholesome and the root of the unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in other words, the sotāpanna is not just someone who got thin or got skinny.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's someone who understands.
[SPEAKER_01]: The path that, regardless of how fat they might be now, it will take them to be skinny at some point.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if like, again, it was a magical button that they pressed, there's absolutely no understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of what is it that that takes you there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, sotāpanna, because actually that happens.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, there's quite often a view that if you just get, like, an experience of cessation of suffering, that qualifies you as a as a stream enterer.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, that's like somebody who... and you don't know how it happened.
[SPEAKER_01]: You were just meditating for, I don't know, intensively for a few weeks, and then this experience came up.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you have to, on top of everything, you have to ask other people
[SPEAKER_01]: That's concerning.
[SPEAKER_01]: This will sound like a joke, but I used to wonder if you could give somebody stream entry with like a VR headset and like the right kind of program put on it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That was...
[SPEAKER_01]: Or hallucination, like, you know, you bring them to hallucinatory state, which is essentially what meditative techniques are doing, and then you kind of induce them, make them think about something while they're in that hallucinatory state.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's literally, like, what people would think of as, you know, why you need samādhi, you know, to then give rise to wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, again, that's just a magic trick.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you haven't understood the root of the unwholesome, in the sense that, as we were saying before, you would be free from doubt in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you would be able to explain to somebody else exactly what they would have to do in order to get to that point.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it wouldn't depend on like, oh, when you're this type of person, you have to do this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or when you have this situation, you have to do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be on a very universal level of what
[SPEAKER_01]: Great aversion and delusion are what you have understood in yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Plus, you've understood how you came to that understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you were to, like, lose that understanding, let's say, out of some... Obviously, that's not going to happen, but theoretically, you would know exactly how to get back to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why you actually wouldn't lose it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that Noble Disciple is sort of in between Putujana and Arahant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, he knows how he became a Noble One.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's one thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: That is sort of retrospectively looking back.
[SPEAKER_02]: These things I did or why it resulted in this right view just now.
[SPEAKER_02]: Being on the path, he knows if I keep doing this, and he's beyond doubt about that, that's going to lead to the complete cessation of suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, this is why it's important to organize one's thinking along those three different kinds of understanding, and not just think, I'm completely confused, and one insight, and everything is going to be solved at once.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and and also, so, because again, you can have that
[SPEAKER_01]: You kind of assimilate it and then say, yeah, I do see that, based on this understanding, if I were to just repeat it, I would eventually get to our answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the question is, like, is it something universal?
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you truly say that it's something universal that you understood?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, that applies to absolutely everyone?
[SPEAKER_01]: To the point where you would have the confidence, actually.
[SPEAKER_01]: When, as the siddhas would say, like, a noble disciple would know there is no ascetic or brahman in the entire universe who could fundamentally rightly disagree with this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he would say it's like a like a strong post that then, you know, whichever direction the wind comes, it wouldn't be able to move it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in the same way, he would say the noble disciple would be perfectly
[SPEAKER_01]: Establishing the view, and to some it might sound like the ultimate close-mindedness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, or like a fundamental belief, except that for him it is now on a longer level of belief.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, because it's, again, so it's these universal truths that you recognize.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even before, it's not that you kind of developed, how to put it, it's not that you kind of... Again, it's not just that you lost weight.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is like something that you did.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's most of the time what people see as mental development.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you understood the principle of losing weight, which was there always.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if you just eat less than you spend, you will lose weight.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you understand that principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's not that in the past,
[SPEAKER_01]: When you weighed, I don't know, 500 pounds, that principle was not there.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: That principle was operating there the whole time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if it's not something universal that you understood, it's like, you just understood, like, if I do this practice like this, in this way, and you have all this sort of system of methods that you bind together, but there's nothing universal about it, and most certainly you would not see that this is what everyone has to do in order to get to stream entry, then that's not a universal insight.